The Life of Muhammadﷺ, The Madinan Period, Volume 1
By Imam Anwar Al_Awlaki,
اَعُوْذُ بِاللهِ مِنَّ الشِّيْطَانِ الرَّجِيْمِ۝بِسْمِ اللهِ الرَّحْمَانِ الرَّحِيْمَ۝
اَلْحَمْدُ لله ، وَالصَّلَاةُ وَالسَّلَامُ عَلى سَيِّدِنَا محمد وَعَلَى اَلِهِ وَصَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرا
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to benefit us all from these sessions
and to make us of those, who follow the best of words and apply them.
Hanzhalah رضي الله عنه, one of Al-Ansaar(الأنْصَار).
He got married right before the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
And his first night with his wife was the night, right before the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Usually the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) should spend that time on base
But Hanzhalah(حنظلة) sought permission from Rasool Allah ﷺ
to allow him to go and spend that night with his wife.
He is newly married, so he went to spend the night with the bride
and early in the morning he goes and prays Fajr(فجر) with the Sahabah رضي الله عنه, with Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and then he goes back home.
And his wife hold on to him
and they sleep together
and since it's getting late, he had to rush out and he did so without making Ghussl(غسل).
He didn't take the shower, from the ritual impurity
and he goes to the battlefield, to fight the battle of Uhud(أحَد).
And Hanzhalah رضي الله عنه, even though he was a foot soldier, he wasn't horseman,
he attacked Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان), who had a horse,
so Hanzhalah(حنظلة) is attacking Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) on foot,
which puts him to a disadvantage.
But he tries and one of the enemy soldiers, strikes him with his spear
and the spear hits him in the torso, and comes out from the other side.
And Hanzhalah(حنظلة), not giving up try to pursue the enemy, who struck him.
So, the enemy attacked him again and hit him another time
and this time it was the fatal blow that killed Hanzhalah رضي الله عنه.
After The battle was over, Rasool Allah ﷺ saw Hanzhalah(حنظلة),
and he saw something strange.
So, he told someone to go and ask his wife about him,
What happened.?
So, they go and ask the wife of Hanzhalah(حنظلة), the wife of Hanzhalah(حنظلة) was Jamila(جميله),
the daughter of the head of Al-Munafiqeen(منافقين), but she was a righteous woman.
Jamila(جميله) and Abdullah(عبدالله) were both righteous children of Abdullah Bin Obaey(عبدالله بن ابيئ),
even though he was the head of Al-Munafiqeen(منافقين).
And he also had a son who was good Muslim, his name was Abdullah(عبدالله).
So, they go and ask Jamila(جميله), they said, What happened?
So, she told them that I slept with my husband, and he didn't make Ghussl(غسل),
and he left in the state of ritual impurity.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
I saw Hanzhalah(حنظلة) right there, between the heaven and earth, being carried by the angels,
and they were washing him with water from Paradise in vessels of silver.
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله), the angels came down to wash Hanzhalah(حنظلة).
And thus, he was called Ghaseel-Ul-Malaikah(غسيل الملائكه), the one washed by the angels.
Another strange thing occurred, and that is,
his wife after sleeping with her husband,
calls in four witnesses to tell them that she has slept with Hanzhalah(حنظلة),
which seems to be a very strange thing and it is,
I mean, a husband sleeps with his wife.
So, why go tell four people about it to be witnesses?
So, they asked her, they said, I mean, why are you telling them, that this happened?
She said, because I saw a dream,
I saw that the sky opened, the heavens opened
and Hanzhalah(حنظلة) went through and then the sky closed.
So I interpreted that dream to mean that Hanzhalah(حنظلة) would die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
Now, why in the world,
would a woman, who just got married,
want to sleep with her husband,
and probably conceived from him,
when she knows that he's gonna die the next day?
Doesn't make sense.
I mean, one would assume that the prudent thing to do, is to try to avoid conceiving from this man
because he would be dead
and that would make it easier for you to get married, after that,
having no children and still a virgin woman.
Why did you hold on to him?
And then go on call four witnesses and tell them what happened?
You see, probably, it's difficult for us, to understand this.
Because see, this shows you that the Sahabah(صحابه) had a different mindset than we did.
They have a different worldview than we do.
They saw things differently, whether we're talking about political matters,
and military matters,
social matters, family matters.
And this is something that it's sad that we see things differently and
when we read about the lives of the Sahabah(صحاله),
we kind of raised our eyebrows and say that this is strange.
But to her this was the right thing to do.
My husband is going to be a Shaheed(شهيد), I want to have a child for him.
And I'm happy that my husband is gonna die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
It's not that I'm sad.
I mean, obviously, a wife wouldn't want her husband to leave her alone in this Duniyah(دُنِيَّا).
But it's for higher cause, it's for the sake of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And she was happy about it.
You might wonder, who would marry her after having a child,
No! Subhan Allah(سبحان الله),
وَمَنْ يَتَّقِ اللَّهَ يَجْعَلْ لَهُ مَخْرَجًا
If you have Taqwa(تقوى), Allah would find a way out for you.
She ends up marrying Talha Bin Ubaid-Ellah(طلحه بن عبيدالله)
one of the great Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
By the way, she did have a son, a child from Hanzhalah(حنظلة) and his name was Abdullah(عبدالله).
And this child was very proud.
When people were asking, who are you?
He would say I'm the son of the one, who was washed by the angels.
Anyways, she got married to Talha(طلحه).
And then Muhammad(محمد), her child from Talha(طلحه), was the one, who was the closest to Abdullah(عبدالله).
And if Abdullah(عبدالله) would need anything, then it was his half brother Muhammad(محمد), who will take care of him.
So, even though Abdullah(عبدالله) would grow up as an orphan,
but Allahعَزّوجَلّ has replaced what he would miss from his father,
and he ended up getting it from his step father and from his half brother.
So, if a person has Taqwa(تقوى), Allahعَزّوجَلّ will replace them with something, that is better.
Allah will make up for you, what you have lost.
Also, I want to point out here to you the level of obedience, that the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم had,
here is a man who just got married
and early in the morning, the next day, he goes willfully to fight in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
And he doesn't just go there to attend,
and to show that he was there,
but in fact, pursues martyrdom,
as we saw, in the case of attacking Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان),
who was the leader of the army and definitely would be well protected.
But he was searching for Shahadah(شهادة), even though I just got married last night.
And I think that brothers, who have experienced marriage
and can go back to the day that they got married,
would realize how attached to Duniya(دنيا), they would be in those particular days.
But the Sahabah رضي الله عنهم, they were connected to Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
We're carrying on with the stories of Shuhadah(شهدآء) from Uhud(أحَد).
Abdullah Bin Amr Bin Haraam(عبدالله بن عمرو بن حرام) he told his son that,
you are the dearest thing to me in this Duniyah(دنيا) after Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and I would have wished you to die as a Shaheed(شهيد).
But I want you to take care of your sisters and to pay my debt.
And that's why his son stayed behind while he went to fight.
And he was killed in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد),
his son Jabir رضي الله عنه, and the family gathered around him and they were weeping,
crying because of the loss of Abdullah Bin Haraam(عبدالله بن حرام).
Rasool Allah ﷺ told them and this is in Bukhari(بخاري),
whether or not you weep for him, the angels went on shading him with their wings,
until you have lifted him up.
Doesn't make a difference if you cry on him or not.
He's happy and then Rasool Allah ﷺ meets Jabir(جابر) and it tells him,
Shall I give you some glad tidings.
Then Rasool Allah ﷺ said;
Allah greeted your father right there at Uhud(أحَد), where he was struck down.
He then asked him.
What is your wish Abdullah(عبدالله).?
Allah u Akbar(الله اكبر), Allahعَزّوجَلّ is talking to His servants and calling him by his name.
What is your wish Abdullah(عبدالله)?
What do you wish Me to do with you?
So, Abdullah(عبدالله) replies,
O Lord, to return me to the world, so that I may fight again for you and be killed once more.
No one, absolutely no one,
wants to go back to Duniyah(دنيا) except the Shaheed(شهيد).
Everybody else would hate to go back to Duniyah(دنيا) and have to go through the agony of death one more time.
But since the Shaheed(شهيد) doesn't taste that,
since the Shaheed(شهيد) doesn't suffer from that
and only feels death, like a thorn or a sting of an insect.
And after they see the great reward that Allahعَزّوجَلّ gives them, they wished to go back.
So, these are some stories of the Shuhadaa(شهداء) of Uhud(أحَد).
Some of the virtues of Shuhadaa(شهدآء),
some of the Ayaat(آيات) and Ahadith(احاديث) that were mentioned,
during the Battle of Uhud(أحَد), regarding the Shuhadah(شهدآء)
and these Ayaat(آيات) and Ahadith(احاديث), even though they were said in the context of the Battle of Uhud(أحَد),
but they apply to any Shaheed(شهيد) at anytime.
Ibn Abbas(ابن عباس) said:
The Prophet told me, when your brothers were struck down at Uhud(أحَد).
Allah place their spirits in the crops of green birds
that would go down to the rivers of Paradise and feed off the fruits there.
Then they would retire to golden candelabra hung in the shade of the throne,
enjoying their food, drink and lodging so well.
They asked, Who can tell our brothers about us
that we are alive in Paradise and being well provided for,
so that they will not shirk Jihad(جهاد) and not be reluctant in warfare.
So, they wanted somebody to go back and encourage their brothers
and told them, carry on fight Fee Sabeel Lillah(في سبيل الله).
And Don't be reluctant to join in, war.
So, Allahعَزّوجَلّ, the Almighty and glorious replied, I will inform them about you.
And so Allah sent down in His book,
verse 169, to 171, in Surat Al-Imran(سورةالعمران).
وَلَا تَحْسَبَنَّ الَّذِينَ قُتِلُوا فِي سَبِيلِ اللَّهِ أَمْوَاتًا ۚ
بَلْ أَحْيَاءٌ عِنْدَ رَبِّهِمْ يُرْزَقُونَ ۝
فَرِحِينَ بِمَا آتَاهُمُ اللَّهُ مِنْ فَضْلِهِ
وَيَسْتَبْشِرُونَ بِالَّذِينَ لَمْ يَلْحَقُوا بِهِمْ مِنْ خَلْفِهِمْ
أَلَّا خَوْفٌ عَلَيْهِمْ وَلَا هُمْ يَحْزَنُونَ۝
يَسْتَبْشِرُونَ بِنِعْمَةٍ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَفَضْلٍ وَأَنَّ اللَّهَ لَا يُضِيعُ أَجْرَ الْمُؤْمِنِينَ۝
And never think of those, who have been killed in the cause of Allah as dead
rather they are alive, with their Lord, receiving provisions,
rejoicing, and what Allah has bestowed upon them, of His bounty.
And they'll receive good tidings about those to be martyred after them,
who have not yet joined them.
That there will be no fear concerning them,
nor will they grieve.
They received good tidings of favor from Allah and bounty,
and of the fact that Allah does not allow the reward of the believers to be lost.
So, number one, the Shaheed(شهيد) is alive.
Number two, they want their brothers to carry on.
And by the way, the bond of brotherhood that develops
between the Mujahideen(مجاهدين) Fee Sabeel Lillah(في سبيل الله) is special.
So, even after they die, they're still thinking about their comrades,
their brothers in arms, the ones that were fighting with them,
because of the special bond that develops among them.
The Shuhadah(شهدآء) of Uhud(أحَد), were so eager to convey a message to their brothers,
who are still alive, that Allahعَزّوجَلّ offered to do that for them.
And Ayaat(آيات) of Qur'an were revealed, to convey that news to their brothers
And these Ayaat(آيات) are still Ayaat(آيات) that we read today.
Abdullah Bin Masood(عبدالله بن مسعود) said, We asked the Messenger of Allah about this verse.
And he replied their souls are in the crops of green birds that fly wherever they want.
So, every one of them has a private jet to take them wherever they want in Jannah(جنه),
they are the pilots and they can fly them wherever they want.
Their souls are in the crops of green birds that fly wherever they want,
then retire to candelabra, hanging near the throne.
Once when they were there, your Lord looked over at them and said,
ask whatever you want.
They replied: What could we have to ask for
flying about anywhere in paradise as we do?
What do you want? I mean, What more can we ask for?
So, Allah repeated His question to them three times.
And when they realize that they would be asked again and again,
They replied, we ask of you, that you return our souls to our bodies on Earth,
so that we may be killed in your cause once more.
And when Allah saw that this was the only request they would make, they were left alone.
Subhaan Allah(سُبْحَان الله) after insisting on them for three times, the only thing that could come up with.
We want to go back and fight for Your sake.
A story mentioned by Ibn Abi Duniyah(إبن ابي دنيا)
narrated by Attaf Bin Khalid(عطاف بن خالد),
he said that his Aunt related to him.
I rode one day to the graves of the martyrs,
something she often did.
And I stopped and prayed for a certain time near the grave of Hamza(حمزه).
There was no one there in the valley except for the youth standing, holding the head of my mount.
When I had finished I made the farewell gesture, indicating, Peace be upon you.
Then I heard the greeting being returned to me,
emanating from beneath the ground,
I am as sure of this, as I am that a mighty and glorious Allah created me.
And as I know night from day every hair of my body stood on end.
So, they responded to her Salaam(سلام), they responded back to her Salaam(سلام).
Rasool Allah ﷺ says that anyone, who goes and visits the grave of the Shuhadah(شهدآء) of Uhud(أحَد)
and gives them Salaam(سلام), they will respond back to it.
Al-Waqidie(ألواقدي), he says: When Muawiyah(معاويه) was about to dig the canal.
This is in the time of Khilafah(خِلَافَه) of Muawiyah(معاويه),
he wanted to dig a canal close to the cemetery of the Shuhadah(شهدآء) of Uhud(أحَد).
He had the crier announced anyone who had relative killed at Uhud(أحَد), should be witness,
because this canal might cut through some of the graves.
He wanted the relatives of the diseased to be there,
so that they would point out whose grave is it and move them as if necessary.
Jabir رضي الله عنه said: A man came to me and said;
Jabir(جابر), Some of Muawiyah(معاويه)'s workers have uncovered your father to site
and part of him is outside the grave.
So, Jabir(جابر) goes and he said, when we dug for them,
I found my father in his grave lying as though asleep unchanged.
We also found that his companion in the grave Amr Bin Jamooh(عمروبن جموح),
had his hand over a wound and when it was removed, the wound emitted blood.
It also says that the spade, struck the foot of Hamza(حمزه) and blood came out.
Jabir رضي الله عنه said; We brought them out as though they had been buried the previous day.
And Ibn Kathir(ابن كثير) said
and it is said that the grave of each one of them may Allah be pleased with them
gave forth a scent like that of Musk.
And how long after had they were burried, did this happen?
46 years later,
it was as if they were just buried
and the smell of Musk was still coming out of their graves.
These are Karamaat(كرامات) of the Shuhadaa(شهدآء).
It is Sunnah(سنة) to bury the Shaheed(شهيد), where they die
and not to move them to a different location.
Because when some of the Sahabah(صحابه), were taking the dead bodies to Madina.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said return them and have them buried at Uhud(أحَد).
And that's where the cemetery of the Shuhadaa(شهدآء) is, it is in Uhud(أحَد),
even though Madina was close by
and they could have carried them to Madina,
but Rasool Allah ﷺ wanted them to be buried in the sight of the battlefield.
So, the scholars say that it's the Sunnah(سنة),
to bury the Shuhadaa(شهدآء), where they die.
Bukhari(بخاري) narrates, that Jabir رضي الله عنه said,
the Messenger of Allah would place, one piece of clothing over each two of the men killed at Uhud(أحَد).
And then would ask which one of these had a better knowledge of Qur'an,
he would then place the one indicated in the grave first saying,
I will testify for these at the Day of Judgment.
So it shows you how poor they were
they couldn't afford wrapping everyone in the necessary shroud, so they had to share.
And also probably because of the exhaustion,
they ended up burning more than one person in each grave.
And they would place the one who memorized more Qur'an first,
and then they would place the second.
Rasool Allah ﷺ ordered that they be buried in their blood,
he did not pray over them,
nor were they washed
and this is also in Bukhari(بخاري).
So, this tells you the Sunnah(سنة), this is that the Shaheed(شهيد) is not washed
and that there is no Salah(صلاة) of Janazah(جنازه) prayed for the Shaheed(شهيد),
because he's not dead
and the prayer of Janazah(جنازه) is for the dead.
And since Shaheed(شهيد) is alive
you don't pray Janazah(جنازه) on them.
And also they be buried in their blood because Rasool Allah ﷺ says on the Day of Judgment,
these injuries and this blood will be emitting the smell of musk.
Rasool Allah ﷺ pray Salah-Tuz-Zuhur(صلاة الظهر)
and as we said: Rasool Allah ﷺ was injured and exhausted.
So, he had to pray sitting down.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ asked the Sahabah(صحابه) to line up because he's going to make Dua(دعا)
and Rasool Allah ﷺ made this following Dua(دعا).
And this is narrated by Imam Ahmad(إمام احمد),
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: "O Allah to You is do all praise,
O Allah, there is no grasping what You have dispersed,
nor dispersing, what You grasped,
there is no guiding aright, those whom You have led astray,
nor any leading astray of those, You have guided,
there is no giving of what You have prevented,
nor any prevention of what You have given,
there is no drawing close, what You have distanced,
nor any distancing, what You have drawn close.
O Allah, spread forth Your blessings, Your mercy, Your generosity and Your favors upon us.
O Allah, I ask you those enduring blessings that never change nor seize,
O Allah I asked you for blessings at time of the provation and security at time of fear.
O Allah, I seek refuge with You against the evil of what You have given us,
as well as from the evil from which You have saved us.
O Allah have us view faith with favor and endear it to us well,
have us view disbelief in morality and disobedience with antipathy.
Place us among those who are well guided.
O Allah take us to Yourself as Muslims,
and give us life as Muslims
Place us among the virtuous,
not the shamed or the demented.
O Allah, do battle with those disbelievers,
who give the lie to your messengers, and who oppose them,
torment and punish them.
O Allah do battle against those disbelievers
who are given the Scripture, Oh God of truth.
This was the Dua(دعا) of Rasool Allah ﷺ after the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Ibn Is'haaq(إبن اسحاق) said: the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) took place on Saturday,
in the middle of Shawwal(شوال).
On the morning of Sunday, the 16th of Shawwal(شوال),
the crier of the Messenger of Allah announced to the people
that they should leave in pursuit of the enemy.
Now the Muslims just came back from battle.
They fought the battle on Saturday and Sunday morning
the announcement is made that you have to pick up your arms
get ready and pursue the enemy again.
Now they are tired, exhausted, injured,
they lost 70 of their men in one day.
And now the next day immediately following the day of the Battle of Uhud(أحَد),
they're supposed to carry on a fight.
So, this was very difficult to them, and the hypocrites didn't want to go out
and they made a big deal out of it.
And they started spreading rumors because rumor came in that
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) and his army are regrouping and planning another attack.
So hypocrites said, Are you crazy?
Abu Sufiyan(ابو سفيان) has won yesterday.
And now they're regrouping and they're receiving reinforcements.
And you want to go and fight them again.
And these rumors were having their effect,
but Rasool Allah ﷺ said, We'll go out and meet them.
And Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق), reveals to us the purpose.
He said, The purpose of the messenger of Allah in pursuing was to frighten the enemy.
This was by making them aware that they were still powerful,
and that their losses had not so weaken them,
that they could no longer face their enemy.
Rasool Allah ﷺ is showing patience,
he's showing steadfastness in face of danger,
and he's showing persistence.
And these are important qualities for the Muslims in their fight with the enemies of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Even if you're defeated, You carry on the fight.
Even if your weakened you depend on Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and you receive strength, from Him,
and you remain steadfast and patient.
I'll read to you what Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق) said about the outcome of this battle.
He said the Khuza'a(خزاعه) tribe,
both those of them who were Muslims and those who were unbelievers
were secretly the allies of Rasool Allah ﷺ in Tahamah(تهامه).
And their understanding with him was that they would not conceal from him anything that happened there.
So, these were tribes living in Tahamah(تهامه) in Hijaaz(حجاز).
And whether the Muslims among them or the non Muslims, they were allies of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and they would bring him information about any movements that would occur in their area.
Ma'bad(معبد) at that time was a Mushrik(مشرك), he was disbeliever.
And he told Rasool Allah ﷺ, on his way past Hamra Al-Asad(حمراء ألأسد),
Muhammad(محمد), we're deeply sorry at what happened to your men
and we hope for Allah to protect you and them.
So, even though it was a Mushrik(مشرك), but he was supportive of Rasool Allah ﷺ
and he said, We wish that you would win against the people of Quraish(قريش).
He then left while Rasool Allah ﷺ was still there at Hamra Al-Asad(حمراء ألأسد),
and met up with Abu Sufiyan Bin Harb(ابو سفيان بن حرب)
and his men at Raohaa(روحاء).
They had decided to return to fight Rasool Allah ﷺ and his men.
They had concluded we have severely damaged the best of his companions,
and their chieftains and nobles.
So, should we now go home before we uproot them completely,
we should go back for the rest of them and be finished with them.
So this was the plan of the Kuffar(كفار).
When Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) saw Ma'bad(معبد) he asked him,
How are things back up behind you Ma'bad(معبد),
he replied; Muhammad(محمد) has come out with his men
seeking you in a force the likes of which I never saw before.
And this wasn't true.
But Ma'bad(معبد) is exaggerating the strength of the Muslims.
They are truly in rage towards you,
he has been joined by those who stayed behind when you did battle with him.
And these men much regret what they did?
The anger they have towards you is something the like of which I've never seen before.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) said; What are you suggesting?
He replied, I swear, I don't think you'll be able to leave
before you catch sight of the forelocks of their cavalry,
meaning they're coming fast.
But we've decided to attack them to destroy the rest of them.
That was the response of Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان).
Ma'bad(معبد) said;
I really do advise you against that I swear.
I was so affected by what I saw that I can post some verses on the subject.
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان) said, What did you compose, Ma'bad(معبد) recited the verses he said,
At the noise my mount almost shied....
The earth streaming with masses of fine horses....
Racing on their riders like noble lions....
men, not effeminate in the fray and not poorly armed....
I ran on thinking the earth itself moving....
as they brought up a leader never to be forsaken....
And I said, Woe to Ibn Harb(ابن حرب)....
When you meet the plane shakes beneath the lions of men....
I warn the people of Makkah very plainly....
Addressing every wise insane man they have....
Of the army of Ahmad(احمد) not some mixed rebel....
And my warning should not be described as mere hearsay....
Abu Sufiyan(ابوسفيان), when he heard this his party were dissuaded and they went back.
So, Ma'bad(معبد) did very well job in demoralizing the enemy and sending them back
by convincing them that they have no chance of winning against Rasool Allah ﷺ and his Sahabah(صحابه).
Allahعَزّوجَلّ revealed Ayaat(آيات)
talking about this incident,
the Munafiqeen(منافقين) saying that the Muslims should not go out and fight
and the confidence that the Muslims had in victory,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ says and these are verses 172 to 175.
الَّذِينَ اسْتَجَابُوا لِلَّهِ وَالرَّسُولِ مِنْ بَعْدِ مَا أَصَابَهُمُ الْقَرْحُ ۚ
لِلَّذِينَ أَحْسَنُوا مِنْهُمْ وَاتَّقَوْا أَجْرٌعَظِيمٌ۝
الَّذِينَ قَالَ لَهُمُ النَّاسُ إِنَّ النَّاسَ قَدْ جَمَعُوا لَكُمْ فَاخْشَوْهُمْ
فَاخْشَوْهُمْ فَزَادَهُمْ إِيمَانًا
وَقَالُوا حَسْبُنَا اللَّهُ وَنِعْمَ الْوَكِيلُ۝
فَانْقَلَبُوا بِنِعْمَةٍ مِنَ اللَّهِ وَفَضْلٍ لَمْ يَمْسَسْهُمْ سُوءٌ
لَمْ يَمْسَسْهُمْ سُوءٌ وَاتَّبَعُوا رِضْوَانَ اللَّهِ ۗ وَاللَّهُ ذُو فَضْلٍ عَظِيمٍ۝
إِنَّمَا ذَٰلِكُمُ الشَّيْطَانُ يُخَوِّفُ أَوْلِيَاءَهُ
فَلَا تَخَافُوهُمْ وَخَافُونِ إِنْ كُنْتُمْ مُؤْمِنِينَ۝
Those believers, who responded to Allah and the messenger
after injury had struck them.
For those who did good among them and feared Allah, is a great reward.
Those to whom the people, i.e. the hypocrites said,
Indeed the people have gathered against you, so fear them.
But it merely increased them in faith.
And they said sufficient for us is Allah, and He is the best disposer of affairs.
So, the true believers in front of these rumors,
which were by Shaytan(شيطان) and the hypocrites with the intention of weakening their morale.
These rumors made them stronger.
And they said;
حسبنا الله ونعمل وكيل,
sufficient for us is Allah and He is the best disposer of affairs.
And then Allah says;
So they returned with favor from Allah and bounty, no harm, haven't touched them.
They didn't even fight
and they pursued the pleasure of Allah.
So, they didn't fight, but they still received the pleasure of Allah
and Allah is the possessor of great bounty,
that is only Satan who frightens you of his supporters
so fear them not but fear Me, if you are indeed believers.
So, Shaytan(شيطان) would come to us and say that
the enemy is powerful, the enemy is strong,
look at his aircraft, look at his tanks, look at his rockets,
look at his weapons, look at the numbers of his army
and Allahعَزّوجَلّ says that, it is just from Shaytan(شيطان), with the purpose of weakening you.
But if you say;
حسبي الله ونعمل وكيل
and if you depend on Allahعَزّوجَلّ, Allah will give you victory.
The only prisoner of war that was taken by the Muslims in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد),
ironically was Abu Azza(ابو عزى).
You remember Abu Azza(ابو عزى),
Abu Azza(ابو عزى) was the one, who was captured by the Muslims in the Battle of Badr(بدر)
and he told Rasool Allah ﷺ that I am poor, and I have daughters.
So, set me free
and Rasool Allah ﷺ set him free, without paying any ransom.
And he took from him an oath that he would never support an enemy against Rasool Allah ﷺ and Abu Azza(ابو عزى) agreed.
But when he goes back to Makkah,
and it's time for the people of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ) to leave for the battle of Uhud(أحَد),
they tell them to join he said no, I've given my word to Muhammadﷺ
that I'm not gonna fight against him.
So, they kept on trying to convince him, until they fooled him and deceived him
and he did join the army
and Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) he ended up as the only one taken as a prisoner of war and this is an Aayah(آية) from Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
Now, he again tries to play the same trick against Rasool Allah ﷺ
by saying that my daughters are in need, I'm a poor man, so set me free.
Rasool Allah ﷺ told him,
I will not let you stroke your beard and say that you have deceived Muhammad(محمد) twice
and he ordered him to be beheaded.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ said, believer will not be bitten twice from the same layer.
So, Muslims should not be fooled, a Muslim should not be tricked
and a Muslim should not be naive.
Give some examples of the good ending and the evil ending because the end is what counts.
Your last moments on this world are very important.
Because your faith depends on your ending in this Duniyah(دنيا).
We have in battle of Uhud(أحَد), examples of good ending and an evil ending.
Kazmaan(كزمان) for example, one of the men from Madina,
he wasn't interested in Islam.
But when the Muslims went out to fight in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد), he joined them,
and whenever the name of Kazmaan(كزمان) would be mentioned in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
he would say;
اِنَّه’ فِيْ النَّارْ
He is in hellfire
But the Sahabah(صحابه) saw that he was fighting like a lion,
and he has killed at least seven disbelievers before he fell due to his wounds.
So, this made some of them skeptical.
I mean, how could this man go to Hellfire when he has fought so hard?
But then they came to him.
Some of the Sahabah(صحابه) came to him and said;
Some of his people from Madina came to him and said; Congratulations for being a martyr
for being a Shaheed(شهيد).
He said, Why are you congratulating me for Shahadah(شهادة).
I didn't fight for the sake of Islam, I fought for the sake of my people.
So, this man is fighting with the wrong intentions
and then he dies.
And he goes to hell fire
because he didn't fight Fee-Sabeel-Lillah(فِي سَبيل الله), he didn't fight for the intention of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
So, this is an example of the evil ending
Mukhaireeq(مخيريق) was a Jew.
He goes to his people and tells them:
O Jews, You have learned,
I swear by Allah, that it is your duty to help Muhammad(محمد) to victory.
They said this is the Sabbath(سابت) we're not gonna fight.
So, he left them and he said;
If I should fall then my wealth goes to Muhammad(محمد) to do with it as he wishes.
So, not only does he joined the Muslims in fighting,
but he also makes his will that his inheritance is taken by Muhammadﷺ to spend as he wishes.
Mukhaireeq(مخيريق) was killed, Rasool Allah ﷺ then said;
مُخَيْرِيْقْ خَيْرُ يَهُوْدْ
Mukhaireeq(مخيريق) is the very best of Jews.
And the Sohaili(سهيلي) said;
The message of Allah converted Mukhaireeq(مخيريق) property consisting of seven orchards into a Waqf(وقف),
charitable endowment in Madina
and Muhammad Ibn Ka'ab Al-Quraidhi(محمد ابن كعب القرظي) said; This was Madina's very first Waqf(وقف).
The first endowment in Madina was that of the Jew, Mukhaireeq(مخيريق).
Now there's a difference of opinion between scholars of whether he embraced Islam or died as a Jew.
With the majority of them saying that he did actually embraced Islam.
And when Rasool Allah ﷺ said that he's the best of Jews.
That means Jews as an ethnicity and not a religion.
So, he's the best of the Jewish people,
but he is a Muslim in faith.
So, that's an example of a good ending.
And then there's Usairym(أصيرم),
who was from Al-Aos(ألاوس), but he wasn't interested in Islam.
He was a Mushrik(مشرك).
He didn't embrace Islam yet.
And when the Muslims left for the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
He said, where is Sa'ad Ibn Muadh(سعد ابن معاد),
they said, he is at Uhud(أحَد),
Where is so and so,
He's at Uhud(أحَد).
Where is so and so, they said, He's at Uhud(أحَد).
So, he said that if all of my people are fighting in Uhud(أحَد), I am going to join them.
And he did join with the Muslims in Uhud(أحَد) and he fought
and he was wounded.
So, before he dies,
some of his relatives come to him and said,
when they saw him, they said; This is Usairym(أصيرم),
as far as we know, he wasn't interested in becoming Muslim.
What is he doing here?
So, they rush up to him and they asked them they asked him, Usairym(أصيرم),
did you fight for the sake of Islam?
Or did you fight for the honor of your people?
He said, No
I fought for the sake of Islam.
So, Usairym(أصيرم) is the opposite of Kazmaan(كزمان).
And then he dies.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ said, he is in Jannah(جنة).
Abu Hurairah(ابو هريره) would later on, ask the people,
he would quiz them, he would say,
Tell me about a man, who entered into Jannah(جنة) without praying one prayer to Allahعَزّوجَلّ
and if they don't know, the answer, he'd tell them, it was Usairym(أصيرم).
Rasool Allah ﷺ said in Bukhari(بخاريْ),
عَمَلًا يَسِيْرًا وَاَجْرًا كَثِيْرًا
He did very little but he was rewarded a lot.
Therefore Shahadah(شهادة) is the one deed
that would guarantee a person the highest levels of Jannah(جنة)
without doing anything else.
Here Usairym(أصيرم) didn't prayed, did not fast, did not do anything.
All what he did was, say
اَشْهَدُ الله اله الا الله وَ اشْهَدُاَنَّ محمد الرَسُول الله
and then he died as a Shaheed(شهيد)
and receives the high levels of Jannah(جنة), great reward.
Some miracles that occurred in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Number one, the eye of Qatadah(قتاده), if I mentioned this as miracle in the Battle of Badr(بدر)
but it is mentioned as miracle in Badr(بدر) and Uhud(أحَد),
there is a difference of opinion among the scholars on where it happened.
Some of them say that it occurred in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
So, we can attribute that to the Battle of Uhud(أحَد) as one of the miracles of the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
Another one is what happened with Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبي بن خلف), one of the leaders of Quraish(قُرَيْشْ),
one of the Mushriqeen(مشركين), one of the worst enemies of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبي بن خلف), he used to say I'm going to kill Muhammad(محمد).
I'm going to kill Muhammad(محمد)
when that news reached to Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: No, I will kill him.
So, in the Battle of Uhud, Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبيئ بن خلف)
charges at Muhammadﷺ on his horse
and he used to feed this horse special food, he used to feed this horse corn
and special food and he would say I'm going to kill Muhammad(محمد) on you.
So, he charges at Muhammadﷺ and the Sahabah(صحابه) say,
they want to volunteer and stop his attack at the Messenger of Allah,
but Rasool Allah didn't allow them.
He said; No, leave him.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ picks up a spear
and he shakes it in his hand
and the narrator said, the Sahabah(صحابه) flew away.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ shook the spear like flies would fly off the back of a camel,
it was such a violent shaking of that spear.
And then Rasool Allah ﷺ throws it at Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبيئ بن خلف),
who was covered in armor, you can only see his eyes.
But there was a small opening between the helmet and the armor on his neck.
And the spear struck him right there.
And it reached to his skin but it couldn't go through because of the steeled armor.
But Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبيئ بن خلف) falls from his horse.
And then he goes back running to his people bellowing like a bull, screaming.
They told him What's wrong with you.
He said: Muhammad(محمد) killed me.
So, they uncovered him and they didn't see any injury in his neck,
all what happened was some blood clotting
because of the impact, but there was no injury.
There was no bleeding, there was nothing.
So, they told him;
لَا بَأسَ بِه
there's nothing wrong with you.?
Why are you so terrified?
He said;
Because Muhammad(محمد) told me that he will kill me,
so if he did nothing but spit on me, I would die.
Subhan Allah(سبحان الله), they believe so much.
They believed with certainty in anything that Rasool Allah ﷺ would say
just because Rasool Allah ﷺ said, I will kill you.
He believed that it would happen as Rasool Allah ﷺ said.
In another narration, he said that
if the pain I'm suffering is distributed among all of the people of Makkah, it would be sufficient to kill them.
And very shortly after he died
and this is a miracle of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
because of the fact that he prophesized that he would kill Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبيئ بن خلف), and it happened.
This is the only person whom we know for certain that Rasool Allah ﷺ killed.
He could have killed many others in battles, but we don't know who they are.?
He is the only one whose name is known.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ says, and this is in Bukhari(بخاريْ) and Muslim(مسلم).
Great is Allah's wrath against the man, whom the messenger of Allah kills, in Allah's cause.
The worst of men is the man on whom a messenger of Allah, any Messenger of Allah would kill.
Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) said, One night while he was traveling the same place  where Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبي بن خلف) was killed.
He said suddenly I saw flames of fire.
And then I saw a man being dragged in chains, asking for water
and the response was don't provide him with any water.
This is a man, who was killed by the Messenger of Allah.
So, Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) was able to see the torment of Obaey Bin Khalaf(أبيئ بن خلف).
And you see, it happens that some men would be able to see either punishment of kuffar(كفار)
or the pleasure of Muslims
that could happen in dreams or it could happen actually in front of you
as what happened with Abdullah Bin Umar(عبدالله بن عمر) here.
And what happened with the Aunt of Attaf Bin Khalid(عطاف بن خالد),
who said that the Shuhadaa(شهدآء) responded to her Salaam(سلام),
so that is something that is of Al-Ghaeb(ألغيب)
but Allahعَزّوجَلّ brings it to the physical world even though it's in the other world,
Allahعَزّوجَلّ reveals that sometimes to his servants.
And we can consider these to be Karamaat(كرامات),
both for this woman and for Abdullah Bin Umar رضي الله عنه.
We'll talk about the role of women and it's important to talk about the role of women
because we want our brothers to have role models
and we also want our sisters to have role models from among As-Sahabiaat(ألصحابيات),
since both brothers and sisters
men and women are far away in their lifestyle from the way of the Sahabah(صحابه),
you see because Islam was best understood by them.
This was the best generation, therefore they are the closest to the truth
and that makes their way the best way.
So whenever you find that
what you're doing is different or your understanding is different than that Sahabah(صحابه)
realize that your way is the wrong way and there's was the right way.
So let's take a look at the As-Sahabiaat(ألصحابيات) in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
They used to provide water and medical assistance.
Anas Ibn Malik(أنس ابن مالك) said;
لَقَدْ رَاَيْتُ عَائشَه بِنْتِ اَبِيْ بَكْرْ وَ اُمُّ سَلِيْمْ
وإنَّهُما لَمُشَمِّرَتَانِ، أَرَى خَدَمَ سُوقِهِن تَنْقُلَانِ القِرَبَ علَى مُتُونِهِمَا،
ثُمَّ تُفْرِغَانِهِ في أَفْوَاهِ القَوْمِ، ثُمَّ تَرْجِعَانِ فَتَمْلَآَنِهَا،
ثُمَّ تَجِيئَانِ فَتُفْرِغَانِهَا في أَفْوَاهِ القَوْمِ
In Bukhari(بخاريْ), Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) said;
I saw Ayesha Bint Abi Bakr(عائشه بنت ابي بكر) and Ummo Salim(ام سليم) tucken up their clothes.
And I could see their legs, their Shin, and this was before hijab
and they were carrying buckets of water on their shoulders,
and they would pour the water in the mouth of the soldiers.
And then they would go back and fill them again and do the same, going back and forth.
And you can also hear, see that
Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله),
Jihad(جهاد) for them was a family effort.
I mean, the women participated in it, the men participated in it.
Here you have Ayesha(عائشه), the wife of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
the wife of the leader, is a servant, is serving the fighters.
I mean, look at the leadership example that Rasool Allah ﷺ was giving.
Ka'ab Ibn Malik(كعب ابن مالك) said;
رَاَيْتُ اُمُّ سَلِيْمْ بِنْت مَلْحَانُ و عَائشَه عَلَى ظُهْورِهِمَا الْقرَبْ
يَحمِلَانَهُمَا يَوْمَ اُحَدْ وَكَانَت حمْنَهْ بِنْتِ جَحَشْ تسْىي الْعَطْشى وَتُداوي الجرحى
وَكَانَتْ اُمْ اَيْمَنْ تَسْقِي الجَرْحَى
Hamna Bint Jahash(حمنة بنت جحش) used to provide water to the thirsty
and she would give medical assistance to the injured
and Umm Aiman(ام ايمن) used to provide water to the injured.
Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) would say,
كَانَ رَسٌول الله صلى الله عليه وسلم يَغْزُوْ بِاُمِّ سَلِيْمْ وَنِسْوَة وَمِنَّ الْاَنْصَارِ مَعَه’ اِذَا غَزَا
فَيَسْقِيْنَ مَاءَ وَيُدَاوِيْنَ الْجَرْحَى
And this is in Muslim(المسلم), Anas Ibn Malik(انس ابن مالك) said;
When Rasool Allah ﷺ would go out to fight in battle.
He would take with him Umm-O-Salim(ام سليم), and some woman from Al-Ansaar(الانصار)
to serve the army.
And this shows you that women would accompany the armies of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
In the time of Umar Bin Khattab(عمر بن خطاب)
he received pieces of cloth, so he was handing them out to the women of Madina.
So, this nice cloth remains and some of the ones who are there said,
O Ameer Ul Momineen(امير المؤمنين) give this to the daughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
your wife and they're referring to the daughter of Ali(علي).
They call her the daughter of Rasool Ullah because she's the granddaughter of Rasool Allah ﷺ,
she's Umm Kalsoom Bint Ali Ibn Abi Talib(علي ابن ابي طالب).
Umar Ibn Al-Khattab(عمر ابن الخطاب) said: No.
Umm-O-Salim(ام سليم) deserves it more.
She was one of the women of Al-Ansaar(الانصار), who gave Baiyah(بيعة) to Rasool Allah ﷺ,
and she was the one giving us water on the day of Uhud(أحَد).
So, Umar رضي الله عنه was recognizing the effort of this woman years later.
He's talking about Umm-O-Salim(ام سليم)
and in this affair, it was the women of Al-Ansaar(الانصار), who deserve special recognition for their effort.
And again, as I said, you'll hear me say again and again
this is what it means to carry the title of Ansaari(انصاري).
Even their woman would give everything for the service of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Fatima(فاطمه) also participated.
Al-Bukhari(البخاري) said: Fatima(فاطمه) washed him, referring to Rasool Allah ﷺ
and Ali(علي) poured the water from a shield.
And when Fatima(فاطمه) saw that the water was only increasing the blood flow
she took a piece of matting and set fire to it,
then attached it to the wound and the blood seized flowing.
We talked about that earlier, when we talked about the injury of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
Not only did the woman act in supporting roles for the army,
like taking care of the injured and delivering water to the soldiers
but there are also incidents where women fought with the sword.
And the example of that would be in Musaibah Bint Ka'ab رضي الله عنها
this was a strong woman
And in Uhud(أحَد) she fought with Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And she fought in more than one battle.
And she even fought in the time of Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه against Musailimah Al-Kazzaab(مسيلمه الكذاب).
And when she died her granddaughter said I was one of those who washed her
and she had 13 injuries in her body.
And the worst of them was the one,
the scar left behind because of the sword of Ibn Qamiyah(ابن قمعة)
Ibn Qamiyah(ابن قمعه), the one who injured Rasool Allah ﷺ, struck her on her shoulder
when she stood in front of Rasool Allah ﷺ to defend him,
and that was the worst of the scars.
And she would suffer other scars in other battles.
And for example, we talked about this in the series on Abu Bakr Siddique رضي الله عنه,
that she suffered injuries in the battle against Musailimah Al-Kazzaab(مسيلمه الكذاب)
and the way those injuries were healed was by pouring boiling oil over them.
And she said that the process of healing was worse and more painful than the injuries themselves.
And for example, this injury here that she suffered from Ibn Qamiyah(ابن قميه) in the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
For one year, she was suffering the pain from that injury.
It took one year to heal.
That was how bad it was,
and Subhaan Allah(سبحان الله) even though she suffered, Allah Ho Alam(الله اعلم) how many injuries on the Battle of Uhud(أحَد).
When Rasool Allah ﷺ was going out to Hamrah Al-Asad(حمراء الاسد), the next day, she wanted to go out.
But when she stood up, she collapsed, she couldn't go any further.
This is how strong the drive in her spirit was.
May Allah be pleased with her.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ went to Hamrah Al-Asad(حمراء الاسد), immediately when he came back
he sent someone to ask about her
and they came back to Rasool Allah ﷺ and said she's getting better.
And Rasool Allah ﷺ was very happy.
And this also shows you another dimension of Rasool Allah ﷺ he cared for the Sahabah(صحابه),
he would ask about them, he wanted to know how well they were doing.
They were on his mind, they were on his mind, he would think about them,
and this is how the leader should be.
Examples of the patience of these Sahabiaat رضي الله عنهن.
Saffiyyah(صفيه) we mentioned part of what happened to her.
Saffiyyah(صفيه) was the sister of Hamzah(حمزه)
and when she received the news that Hamza(حمزه) was killed
she wanted to go and take a look at his body
and we mentioned that when Rasool Allah ﷺ saw her, he told Az-Zubair(الزبير) to go and stop her.
So, Az-Zubair(الزبير) stops her and she pushes him aside and said;
بلغني أنه مثل بأخي وذلك في الله فما أرضانا بما كان من ذلك لأحتسبن و لأصبرن إن شاء الله
Why are you stopping me?
I have been told how my brother has been mutilated
That was in Allah's cause.
And that fact has comforted us
I will keep myself under control and remain calm if Allah wills it
and he was mutilated badly.
I mean, they cut his nose, his ears, his private parts, they opened up his stomach and chest.
So he was badly disfigured.
But she insisted on seeing him and Rasool Allah ﷺ let her see him.
And she went and stood over the body of Hamza رضي الله عنه.
Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق) said; she looked at him,
She said a prayer over him,
asked forgiveness for him,
and then spoke the words to Allah we belong and to Him do we return.
إِنَّا لِلّهِ وَإِنَّـا إِلَيْهِ رَاجِعونَ
This is how, we should dealt with the calamity of losing your brother and seeing him in that condition
I want you to take a moment and think about the meanings of these words.
This is what we say when a disaster befalls us
إِنَّا لِلّهِ
We belong to Allah.
Meaning if I lost a loved one
that loved one belongs to Allah.
And if I think that anything belongs to me, in Duniyah(دنيا), No
me and my belongings belong to Allahعَزّوجَلّ if that's the case,
then it is the property owner,
who has the right to call in, his property and claim it whenever he wants.
If Hamza(حمزه) belongs to Allah,
then Allah is the One, Who has the right to call him in, whenever He wants.
This is very important for the Muslim to realize that
I might have wealth in my hand now.
I might have a family whom I consider to be my family.
But in reality, all of this property of Allahعَزّوجَلّ.
And then;
وَإِنَّـا إِلَيْهِ رَاجِعونَ
And we're going to go back to Him.
Eventually, we're going to go back to Him.
So, I shouldn't be so upset, if I lose something now
because eventually everything is going to go back to Him.
So, it's gonna happen,
regardless it shouldn't make much of a difference if it happens today or tomorrow.
Another example Hamna Bin Jahash(حمنه بنت جحش).
Hamna Bin Jahash(حمنه بنت جحش) is the sister of Abdullah Bin Jahash(عبدالله بن جحش).
And we talked about what happened to Abdullah Bin Jahash رضي الله عنه
and her father also died and her husband Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) died.
So, she lost the three closest men to her.
She came to meet the army
I mean she was there with the army as we said that she was delivering water to them
but when the news was brought to her,
they told her, your father has passed away.
She said;
إِنَّا لِلّهِ وَإِنَّـا إِلَيْهِ رَاجِعونَ
She was composed.
They told her, Your brother Abdullah(عبدالله) has died
And she was also calm and she said;
إِنَّا لِلّهِ وَإِنَّـا إِلَيْهِ رَاجِعونَ
Patient,
and then they said, And your husband Mus'ab Ibn Umair(مصعب ابن عمير) died
and then she screamed.
When Rasool Allah ﷺ saw that he said?
A woman's husband has a very special place with her.
That's the narration of Ibn Is'haaq(ابن اسحاق),
and in the narration of Ibn Majah(ابن ماجه),
Rasool Allah ﷺ said: A husband alone, has control over part of his wife's feelings.
So, the husband is special to his wife.
And she was composed when, she heard the news of her father and brother.
But when she heard the news of her husband, that was too much and then she broke down,
when they asked her, why.?
She said;
That is because I remember that my children will be orphaned.
Rasool Allah ﷺ made Dua(دعا) for her.
Another example is a Dinariya(ديناريه).
She lost her husband, brother and father.
They came to her and said your husband, brother and father were killed.
She said and how is the Messenger of Allah?
they said; he is fine, he's just as you might wish.
She said show him to me.
I want to see him.
And when Rasool Allah ﷺ was pointed out to her, she said every loss other than you is trivial.
It doesn't matter what I lose, whatever I lose is trivial.
As long as, you are fine.
And dear brothers and sisters,
We talked a lot about loving Rasool Allah ﷺ, we talked a lot about sacrifice,
and you see these will remain intangible theoretical concepts
until we see how the Sahabah(صحابه) lived them.
If you want to know what it means to take a look at this woman.
She receives the news of the death of her husband, father and brother
and she only thinks about Rasool Allah ﷺ, how is he.?
And when she knows that he's alive.
She wants to see him, she wants to satisfy her eyes with getting a glimpse of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
And then she says everything, everything is trivial,
as long as you are fine.
This is what it means to love Rasool Allah ﷺ.
We ask Allahعَزّوجَلّ to make us of those who love Him
and to love His messenger
and to love the Sahabah(صحابه) of Rasool Allah ﷺ.
صَلَّى الله عَلى سَيَّدِنَا محمد وَعَلى اَلِهِ وَ صَحْبِهِ وَسَلِّمْ تَسْلِيْمًا كَثِيْرًا
وَالسلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته